Guide to the Civil War Manuscripts Map Collection, 1861-1865 RL.00281
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Civil War Manuscripts Map collection
1861-1865
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.00281
1 Linear Feet 14 items
Sketch maps from the Civil War period representing geographic areas in Virginia, Tennessee, Kentucky, North Carolina, South Carolina, Mississippi, Alabama, Louisiana, and one unidentified location. These maps chiefly depict roads, waterways, mountain ranges, fortifications, counties, cities, and towns. There are two battlefield maps present, including Bull Run (Va., 1861; a Confederate map) and Spring Hill (Tenn., 1864). Most maps are unsigned; however, there are maps drawn by A. M. Thornton, Barbette Sims, and Edward Fontaine, as well as Confederate Army engineers A. B. DeSaulles and Jeremy F. Gilmer. Primarily drawn in ink on paper or linen cloth. Sizes of maps vary between 24 x 20 cm. and 63 x 60 cm.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Collection Overview
Sketch maps from the Civil War period representing geographic areas in Virginia, Tennessee, Kentucky, North Carolina, South Carolina, Mississippi, Alabama, Louisiana, and one unidentified location. These maps chiefly depict roads, waterways, mountain ranges, fortifications, counties, cities, and towns. There are two battlefield maps present, including Bull Run (Va., 1861; a Confederate map) and Spring Hill (Tenn., 1864). Most maps are unsigned; however, there are maps drawn by A. M. Thornton, Barbette Sims, and Edward Fontaine, as well as Confederate Army engineers A. B. DeSaulles and Jeremy F. Gilmer. Primarily drawn in ink on paper or linen cloth. Sizes of maps vary between 24 x 20 cm. and 63 x 60 cm.
Louisiana -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Maps, Manuscript; Manuscript maps; Tennessee -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Maps, Manuscript; Virginia -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Maps, Manuscript; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Maps, Manuscript; Alabama -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Maps, Manuscript; Sketch maps; North Carolina -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Maps, Manuscript; Kentucky -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Maps, Manuscript; Mississippi -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Maps, Manuscript; South Carolina -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Maps, Manuscript; Thornton, A. M.; Gilmer, Jeremy Francis, 1818-1883; Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library; De Saulles, A. B.
- 1861: Virginia
  Scope and Contents note
  Principally a map of the towns of Harrisonburg and New Market west to the Shenandoah Mountains showing roads, waterways, churches, and topography. Pencil and colored ink on paper. Scale, 4:10. 42 x 43 cm.
- 1861: Virginia.
  This is a Map of Portsmouth, Norfolk City and surrounding vicinity by A. M. Thornton [verso] showing the Dismal Swamp, waterways and the Cheasepeake Bay, military and naval sites, and the location of fleets, with notations. Pencil and ink on paper. Scale,1:[1]? 24 x 20 cm.
- 1861-1865: Virginia
  Map of the region between the Potomac and Rappahanock Rivers showing Caroline, Stafford, King George, Richmond, Essex, and Westmoreland counties. Roads and waterways are shown in detail. Colored ink on paper. 41 x 26 cm.
- 1861-1865: South Carolina and North Carolina.
  Map of South Carolina and Mecklenburg Co., N.C. Routes taken by Nathaniel Greene and Daniel Morgan during the American Revolution are shown as well as cities and rivers. Mutilated. Ink on paper. 50 x 36 cm.
- 1861-1865: Tennessee.
  Map of some roads, railroads, and waterways as well the location of the 1st and 2nd Divisions. Dept. Tenn. is noted at the top of the map. Pencil and ink on paper. Scale, 4:1. 32 x 41 cm.
- 1862-1864: Louisiana.
  De Saulles, A. B. Map of Baton Rouge showing streets and roads, a garrison, and a powder magazine as well as the Mississippi River. Ink on paper. 35 x 42 cm.
- 1862-1864: Louisiana.
  De Saulles, A. B. Port Hudson and Vicinity showing roads, plantation lands, and the Mississippi River. Colored ink on linen cloth. Scale, 2:1. 46 x 44 cm.
- 1862-1865?: North Carolina.
  Plan of New Bern showing defenses and Union hospitals. Ink on linen. Scale, 1":400'. 53 x 61.
- 1864: Georgia.
  Map of the East Point and Jonesboro region showing roads, railroads, and the movements of the 15th, 16th, and 17th Union Army Corps. Ink on linen. Scale, 1:1. 30 x 19 cm.
- 1864: Georgia.
  Map of the East Point and Jonesboro region showing roads, waterways, railroads, and the movements of the 15th, 16th, and 17th Union Army Corps. Ink on paper. Scale, 1:1. 30 x 29 cm.
- 1864: Kentucky and Tennessee.
  Map of eastern Kentucky and northeastern Tennessee showing the Cumberland Gap; waterways, including the Cumberland and Powells rivers; roads; topography; and towns. Distances between points are given in some instances. Legend included. Colored ink on paper. 26 x 37 cm.
- 1864: North Carolina.
  Country from New Bern to Kinston showing waterways, roads and railroads, with legend. Ink on paper. Scale, 1:4.. 26 x 39 cm.
- 1864: Mississippi and Alabama.
  Outline Map of the Country Around Verona... [verso] showing roads and railroads; cities and towns;waterways; and counties in eastern Mississippi and western Alabama. Colored ink and watercolors on paper. Scale, 1:5. 63 x 60 cm.
- 1865: Virginia.
  Maj. Gen. J. F.Gilmer. Map Of The Counties Lying Between The James And Rappahanock Rivers, East of Richmond and Fredericksburg. Made under direction of A. H. Campbell, Captain P. E. chief Top' l Dept. D. N. Va. Depicts roads; counties, particularly Gloucester, Middlesex, and Queen Anne; waterways, cities and towns, and railroads. Notation. Colored ink on linen. Scale, 1:4. 60 x 52 cm.